Wow, it's so much brighter out here.
>> It is. It's, you know, the future is
bright.
>> There's lens flare in the future.
>> Yeah. So, uh, welcome everybody to the
Oscars of optimism that, of course,
we're opening up the summit with the
king of autonomous weapon systems.
[laughter]
All right. So, uh, I want to start with
the fact that we're awarding three X
prizes this week. Palmer,
congratulations for winning our, uh,
Wildfire X-P prize.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Yeah, [applause]
>> this one's been a long time. And in
>> it has Let's get Let's get the uh the
the slide up here. So, Palmer won $2.2
million for Ander
>> as if you need it. um a million of
>> a million of that from Lockheed,
>> which was kind of interesting.
>> We do a lot of work with Lockheed. We
also compete with them, but we in the in
the defense space, it's uh you know, we
we compete with their fighter jet
division and we partner with them on
some of their payloads. And so we do a
lot of stuff together. But me and you
have both been trying to get this
autonomous firefighting stuff going for
a long time. For a while.
>> I mean, you got this prize announced
back in 2019. It's been a long time. And
one of our first two products was an
autonomous firefighting tank that we
started building in 2017, finished in
2019.
>> It's insane that we let fires become
conflrations before you put them out.
>> And well, and and it's kind of insane
that uh people are saying, "Oh, that you
know, the technologies finally made this
possible." And I I'm not going to
correct him too often in public, but
it's I mean, this has been possible for
over a decade. It's just that uh
>> let's watch it's become politically
politically impossible to ignore the
problem. out. I'm going to watch a one
minute video clip of what your team
achieved and if you'd walk us through it
here.
>> Sure. So you this was uh an example of
what we were doing at the test site
where we were uh detecting fires,
classifying fires. What you don't really
see in here is that you also [music]
need to reject false fires. That was
part of the test as well. So you have to
know, you know, who's a guy smoking a
cigarette, who's a guy, what's what's a
campfire, what's a road flare, and then
what's something that shows the
characteristics of real fire? That's
what you need to flag to people. That's
what you need to flag to emergency
services. Uh and then you need to
matchmake the type of fire to the right
asset that's in the area. And so you
want to basically use the most cost
effective thing that can respond and get
there in time. And if something's
growing faster, you might need something
different. If it's in woods versus on a
brush hill, you might need something
different. And so, you know, it's it's
it's about detection, classification,
rejection, matchmaking, and then going
and and hitting the target. And the last
thing I'll say is that with most of what
we do, uh, our work with the military,
you go through many of these same steps,
but if you find a target, let's say it
takes you, you know, an hour to an hour
to to get to somebody versus 10 minutes,
it usually doesn't make as much of a
difference. When you're talking about
fire though, the difference between 10
minutes and an hour response, totally
different tools you're going to need to
respond with. You know, a bomb is is is
a is a bomb whether or not it takes a
day or an hour or a minute to get there.
Uh but when when a fire is is is
metastasizing, you need to pick the
right thing that can put it out before
it gets too large.
>> Amazing. you know, uh, we're going to be
announcing something in a month's time,
uh, that you're funding a new X-P prize
and, uh, it's going to be secret until
then, but we're going to tease it now.
Uh, another $10 million prize. Would you
share share with us what we're going to
do?
>> Sure. you know, uh, the, you know, we we
should we should keep the details secret
because there's there's some there's
some good twists, but suffice to say
that, uh, I'm not I'm not interested in
joining the race to push AI forward with
my money. I think that the the the the
artificial intelligence side of models
is is is pretty well covered by plenty
of people. I think we've not been doing
enough understanding biological
intelligence, particularly beyond
people. And so this is going to be a
prize around understanding how animals
think and making so that we can
communicate with them 10 times better
than the current state of the art for
the current smartest species. And not
just trained animals but wild animals in
their own in their own language.
Amazing. [applause and cheering]
And I think that there's actually a lot
that we're going to be able to learn. I
mean if you look at uh large language
models, they're kind of this, you know,
they're they're based on uh humanity's
way of thinking and communicating
distilled. And I think that there's
plenty to learn from all of the other
species that are on this planet. And I
wouldn't be surprised if it has
applications for for AI, particularly
AI, where you need to be uh more
efficient, you know, more power
efficient, more time efficient, uh you
know, a a different point of view, two
heads are better than one, whichever uh
whatever metaphor you want to use.
>> Love it. Love it. All right. I'm going
to kick off the first official question
here. Poom, you're in the AI industry,
the defense industry. What's your P
doom?
I'm just not worried uh about AI dooming
the I guess I'm not worried about AI
doing the killing. I'm very very worried
about evil people using moderately
competent AI to do evil things.
>> Exactly.
>> And I am
>> kind of frustrated by a lot of people
who are new to the dooming hobby. Um,
and and it's it's it's sort it's sort of
like how we had to deal with uh you the
war in Ukraine happens and all of a
sudden all these people who have had the
dumbest opinions you've ever heard about
the military for their whole life. Uh,
and people who believed we lived at the
end of history, that we had moved past
conflict, that we lived in a world where
you could just write a nasty letter in
the UN, forgetting that that only works
if it's backed up by credible threat of
violence. And and all of a sudden they
change their minds. You're seeing this
with AI. People who have not thought
about this problem for more than a
couple years or maybe even just a couple
months uh are are saying, "Oh my god,
this is the biggest threat to humanity."
And these are people who have spent
almost no time actually analyzing what
the largest threats to humanity are.
They haven't spoken to any of the
experts in this area. They certainly
weren't buying freeze-dried food and
building prepper bunkers, you know, like
like like like me and many of my my my
buddies uh who who have indulged
fantasies about what doom could look
like and also thought realistically
about it. And so uh yeah, the AI doom is
way down the list for me. I'm I'm I'm a
big optimist. I think it's going to
massively reduce the cost of resource
extraction, processing, transformation.
You're going to see every part of
society become subject to the same
economies of scale and efficiency that
automated industries that automated
without AI have seen. So think like
agriculture or uh or textiles. You can
buy 2 weeks of calories for less than
one hour of federal minimum wage labor.
That's crazy.
>> Let's give it up for for Palmer here.
>> You're going to see that for everything,
>> Dave. [applause]
So, I I got a really um pressing
question on my mind. I'm kind of a feeds
and feeds and chips and AI foundation
models guy. And so, uh when you're
putting systems in the field, weapons in
the field, uh you can you can put the
intelligence inside it, and this has
always been a big problem for the Air
Force, like if we're going to start
flying drones instead of pilots, who's
going to unleash the weapons, and how's
that decision going to get made? And the
the downside of transmitting it back to
headquarters is you have latency. Uh the
upside is you have a lot more compute.
uh what you can put locally in a device
in a robot in the field in a plane is
limited but it's really really fast. So,
what's your philosophy on like, you
know, I think a lot of people would say,
well, are we going to have
self-contained decision-making weapons
wandering around enemy territories or
are we going to like are we going to
have, you know, control at the
headquarters? How does it work?
>> More or less. The the real concern isn't
so much the latency or or or the speed
of computation. The problem is that if
you rely on uh you know central a
central location to do your compute, you
now need to have command and control
that has uh good high bandwidth
communication back and forth between you
and potentially thousands or tens of
thousands of active assets. And if your
enemy jams your communications or
intercepts your communications or hacks
your communications, you're done. uh or
worse they just skip targeting all the
stuff in the field and they go for the
place where it's all being controlled.
You know, we saw we saw this I there was
a there was a there there was there was
this documentary that George Lucas was
working on and and the Trade Federation
they had they had their central AI
command and control blown up and that
was how the battle of Ne of Naboo
actually resolved was all all the battle
droids lost.
>> Oh yeah. They all fell over.
>> That's right. and they all fell over.
And so I think that that's that that's
the practical reality that's driving the
need to have autonomy living not back
home but forward. There's other areas
like uh you go underwater, you can't
talk to things
>> and sometimes you could talk to things
but you don't want to. Having radio
emissions actually exposes you
necessarily and so you for better or for
worse you're going to need this. I
actually don't think it's as much of a
shift as people think. Um, I there's a
lot of people who look at they say, "Oh
my god, Pandora's box is being opened.
You're going to have weapons that are
making their own kill decisions, and
they don't recognize the reality, which
is that that's been the case for
decades. Uh, you look at the you look at
the the you look at the Aegis system on
destroyers. It has a fully autonomous
mode. You can flip a button and it will
shoot down anything that comes within
whatever range you programmed it with uh
without any human confirmation. Uh you
look at SeaWiz and CRAMM for shooting
down incoming missiles, incoming mortar,
incoming artillery fire, incoming
missiles or incoming speedboats. Uh same
thing, you can put them in fully
autonomous modes. And I mean it going
back to in into Vietnam, we had missiles
that you could launch from an aircraft.
They flew over the horizon, tried to
identify the right radio emitters that
they believed corresponded with a
surfaceto-air missile site, and then
struck them without any, you know, the
person had to decide, I'm going to send
it in this area. they're going to look
for this signal and I know that there's
this probability they're going to get it
right. That decision is going to remain
with people. But uh autonomous weapons
are uh widely widely there's a whole
another talk we're not going to have
today. But I I will I I do have a rant
about this where actually autonomous
weapons have existed for thousands of
years. If you look at and they're
defined as kind of weapons that can
execute the intent of uh what you
program to do independent from the
operator or the engineer. You look at,
for example, pitfall traps that allow
people to walk over them, but then
capture the commander on his horse when
he walks by and it's heavier. You look
at uh certain poison traps that would uh
that would uh kill people who had who
had certain characteristics, not kill
people who had other characteristics or
not kill animals. Uh you look at many
types of landmines and sea mines and
even even torpedoes. And so it depends
on on your exact definition, but even
going into myth where people are
creating golems that can, you know, go
out and fight on their fight on their
behalf or or defend you defend their
city. I I guess my argument is we've had
autonomous weapons for a very very long
time. Uh it's just a new set of
technology that's that's making them
better.
>> So technical question on that. The
foundation models that go into those
those remote systems right now.
>> Yeah. Well, so the the right right now
the open source models are all Chinese.
So I'm pretty sure you're not going to
be putting Chinese models into remote
weapons. Are you going to build and
foundation models or how are you going
to get AI in those devices? I mean,
we've been doing it since 2017. So we're
way ahead of everybody. We're we're
we're a decade beyond that question. Um
I think that we also don't the
foundation models that people are
building are not the types of models you
want to be doing this. They're non
they're largely non-deterministic.
they're non auditable. It's it's a very
different category. The thing that we
are building unfortunately has very few
consumer applications
>> and vice versa. There of course are LLM
use cases for defense that make a lot of
sense, but it's not guiding my missile
or or classifying radar, you know, radar
radar radar feeds. I mean, and we we're
also we can't build models that ingest
text and then spit out text. I need to
process raw data radar data feeds. I
need to process sonar data from passive
listening stations on submarines. That's
it's it's pretty highly specialized. And
I I will take some credit here. Uh all
these people who are talking about how
AI is going to change everything, they
are mostly uh recent converts. And
Industries, you might notice the acronym
is AI. Um so and that that was not that
was not a mistake.
>> Okay,
>> Alex, jump in. Yeah, I think maybe
dovetailing on our discussion of driving
bench, we're now in an era when it's
possible to take frontier models, drop
them into a robotic embodiment and get
pretty stunning results. So, I'd love to
ask you a question maybe about the
scaling hypothesis as it applies to
autonomous weapon systems or autonomous
systems in general. If you have to
extrapolate out, is there a Moors law?
Is there an experience curve for what a
as obviously the capabilities of
underlying frontier models whether
they're from Frontier Labs proper or
from AI as as those progress do we see
any equivalent of a Moors law for the
autonomous systems themselves and and
maybe the the second half of the
question would be do you think
ultimately we achieve some sort of
convergence you'll it makes a variety of
embodiment in a variety of different
form factors
Do you see ultimately some general
purpose category killer robot that is
equivalently the generalist robotic
embodiment just like we now have
generalist models that are capable of
doing substantially any task?
>> No, I don't think so on the defense
side. I think that for manufacturing and
for hospitality and medicine, you might
see this because you get economies of
scale that uh that that are really that
are really material for those types of
businesses. And you know, a humanoid
robot may not be the optimal form for a
burger griller, and it may not be the
optimal form for a firefighter. It may
not be the optimal form for a for a
nurse [laughter] or an assembly
technician.
>> Selma is smiling.
>> But even if it's not optimal, the fact
that it is shared with humanity in its
form makes it a really, really good form
factor. And now I can make one robot
that does all of these things. And uh I
I would probably rather have a let's say
robot that's 5% slower or or uh you know
less reliable than the optimal burger
flipping robot if I can share
commonality with that with that nurse.
In defense, that's not really the case.
Uh- because you are in this constant
race to not just barely beat your
adversary, but to massively overpower
them, to try and make it where you the
goal is not to just barely win a
conflict on the margins. It is to fight
unfair, to have overwhelming threat of
violence underpinning whatever
diplomatic overtures or negotiations you
have. And and and everyone's always
pushing the limit. So if if I if I have
a jet that has a reliable 5% every time
edge over the enemy, that's worth paying
a lot of money for, right? Like I I I
and and I think the the the
loss in performance you would see
through lack of specialization probably
makes it nonviable. like to to to go to
the to the extreme like uh you know I
build robot submarines and those have a
specialized form that needs to dive to
6,000 meter depth and and sit on the
bottom of the ocean for months at a time
and then I have other stuff that's on
the surface and uh and you know they're
robotic systems that you know roll up a
hill and and they loiter and then I have
other things that are you know aerial
vehicles that are doing very specialized
tasks and I just can't imagine a
convergence that would make sense unless
you're telling me that we're going to
get something cool like like humanoids
that have like you know onboard fusion
reactors and they could dive to 6,000 ft
depth.
>> So Palmer, why why aren't you building
those? I mean, if anybody you should
[laughter]
it's look, you could potentially build
such a thing. But then very quickly you
realize that specialization would allow
you to build something even better. You
say, okay, I've built something that can
dive to the bottom of the ocean and fly
to the moon. Man, it could get to the
moon a lot faster if it didn't have to
also dive to the bottom of the ocean. So
I think I think defense is going to be
this one where kind of like uh you know
you you look at for example the
difference between cars where everything
has shared platforms within a
manufacturer you know manufacturer and
they also share a lot of the same
standards uh and interfaces. Uh I think
that you compare that with like uh
motorsport where it's all completely
different and it's continuously pushing
forward. I I think the defense side is
probably always going to be this this
weird branch of exotic, highly
specialized robotic systems.
>> You know, Palmer, I expected if anybody
was going to be building humanoid
robots, it would be you.
>> You said you said absolutely not.
>> I' I've opted out because um I because I
believe in them. If I didn't believe
that humanoid robotics had such a
powerful future, then I would probably
build them. But I want Andreal to build
things that wouldn't exist otherwise.
That's what I generally want. You want
to maximize your marginal impact, but
they
>> correct? All the other people are
already doing a great job. Like I I want
to use their robots and and and do
things with them. Like I think humanoids
are going to be an incredible general
artificial intelligence interface
between AI and remote systems and a lot
of legacy platforms that were designed
for a person, you know, pull the lever,
push the button, read the screen. Like
we're going to be able to take all those
and automate them without replacing them
entirely. So, you have a lot of things
like radar systems that cost millions,
tens of millions, even hundreds of
millions of dollars. Uh, nobody wants to
man them during a hot conflict because
they're the first thing that's going to
go. But if I can put humanoid robots in
them, I've now been able to automate
them without that. So, yeah, I'm not
going to build humanoids. Uh, this is
also why Andre is not building like
small quadcopter attack drones. Too many
other companies doing a great job.
There's there's a lot of a lot of areas
and and we're not going to do space
launch like we do space products. We
have a lot we operate a lot of our own
satellites and a lot of our own sensors
in space. Uh but I don't want to be a
launch provider. That's for all the
other billionaires to
>> Yeah. Yeah. Let let them handle that.
That's fantastic. Sm um you know when
you're operating Andreal Industries,
you're uh decentralizing defense, right?
The Pentagon and Ministries of Defense
globally have been the most centralized
entity in the history of humanity. Uh
you're sitting on the edge dealing with
that. uh you must have a massive immune
system problem where people inside the
entity are going, "No, we've done that
before. We can do it better. They either
try and suck you in or they try and spit
you out." How are you navigating that
interface? Because you're doing it in a
way that I've never seen anybody succeed
do it.
>> I think that this is a problem that's
very very hard at the beginning.
>> Oh, I said the wrong thing. [laughter]
>> Wow. No idea. Well, until someone gets
on the intercom and tells us to go a
million dollar.
>> Congratulations.
>> Um, what were we talking?
>> Seriously, I knew the intercom was going
to come on.
>> What were we talking about again?
>> Centralization of Pentagon versus
decentralized
>> I'm going to keep talking to.
Um,
>> so we've gotten through this a bit. I
think early on there was that concern
that Anderl was not going to be able to
get through that. Our our hardest
problem raising money.
>> Skippy, would you please shut this down?
[laughter]
>> I've been through enough of these to to
know know how it's going to work. There
we go.
>> I imagine.
>> Um, one of our early problems was that
our investors said, Palmer, you
potential investors. They said, "Look,
we believe that you'll be able to build
things that work. We believe you'll be
able to build products that are great,
but we don't believe the government is
capable of actually purchasing them at
scale." Because I mean you talk you talk
about centralization you know about the
issues for people who don't uh until
just a few years ago you had about 80%
of uh MDAPs major defense acquisition
programs so basically anything that that
matters uh 80% of MDAPs went to five
companies and that's it
>> and uh I mean you've seen incredible
consolidation centralization and has
been successful because we use we're
less of a contractor and more of a
product company. We use our own money to
build products. Then we sell them. And
we've gotten to the point now where
people in government have done very very
well betting on and then miraculously we
finish on schedule. We finish on time
and then the next program manager says,
"I know how I can make my job easy. I
just I just give the contract to Ander."
>> Got it.
>> So it's got to take guts to enter the
defense industry, right? The most
incestuous, you know, self-licking ice
cream cone on the planet.
>> Yeah. and and and what insanity,
you know, gave you the balls to do that?
>> The insanity was the reason that I got
into it. Uh the first page of our pitch
deck said Andro will save taxpayers
hundreds of billions of dollars a year
by making tens of billions of dollars a
year. The idea being we're not just
making products that we're selling, but
we are displacing the systems that cost
needlessly 10 times what they should.
And yeah, thank you. [applause]
And so it does seem crazy, but you know,
um I don't I I I can't put myself on the
same pedestal as him, but one of my
mentors and idols growing up and then
also early in my career was John
Carmarmac, the founder of Software.
>> John is great.
>> John is incredible. And for people who
don't know, he's basically inventor of
the modern modern 3D game engine
firsterson shooters. Also started a
rocket company that competed in He he
was competing in the X-P prize and I I
remember
>> and he was one of the if not the only
one to be doing reusable vertical.
>> Exactly. He was doing vertical takeoff
vertical.
>> Nobody else was even trying to do
>> and I remember I remember there's this
this name on the side of his vehicles
Nvidia. How do you pronounce that thing
if I would only know?
>> That's right. He was use and so yeah he
was using uh he was using uh yeah he was
building his own sensor fusion
algorithms. He was processing them on
modern or on a you know like commercial
style graphics card hard hardware using
his game programming experience. Anyway,
the point is
>> it was called Armadillo Armadillo
Aerospace. That's right.
>> And the thing and yeah, they were doing
vertical takeoff and landing long before
SpaceX was uh was was was I mean doing
anything.
>> Yeah. No, before it existed for sure.
>> That's right. And uh so but anyway, the
point is he he um I I he ended up
becoming the CTO of Oculus VR. I managed
to poach him away from ID, but after he
left, he went to work on AI actually
even before I did. Um and so he started
he started his own company to work on uh
on on AGI. And um and I said, "Why why
are you why are you doing this?" you
know that the odds of you succeeding and
to be clear I still believe AI was going
somewhere but he said I'm going to start
a company that's just going all in on
the end state like I'm not trying to
incrementally get there it's just all in
on AGI and the point that he made was
Palmer even if I've got a 1% chance of
succeeding which maybe is an
overestimation but suppose I have a 1%
chance of succeeding and suppose that I
could pull it off uh
the uh the risk adjusted uh outcome kind
of demands that I do it. And that was
how I felt about defense. If there was a
1% chance that I could help solve this
problem, then it was one that would be
massively impactful to work on versus,
let's say, starting another gaming
company, getting into space launch, uh,
you know, building a car company, uh,
that that which it it all of the
billionaires, they end up doing the same
thing. You don't have enough people
getting into defense or or putting on a
bat suit. It's just it's just cars and
rockets and and they just go in circles
like that for for for
>> So, you know, when I interviewed you on
the on the Moonshots podcast last time,
you mentioned that you're part of a
billionaires boys club chat group.
>> Yeah. Yeah. [clears throat] Oh, yeah.
>> Are they working on anything worthwhile
at this point? I mean, I g I gave them
for saying like, "God, you got all
this capital. Solve the world's biggest
problems."
>> I think the B boys are doing a lot
better now than we were a few years ago.
>> Okay.
>> Um
>> they're they're stepping up.
>> Yeah. And for people the thing we're
talking about is I I was giving a lot of
people a hard time especially some
retired B boys and uh I was telling them
what are you what are you doing you have
cuz money is one of the resources they
have but one of the resources people
don't talk about especially for the
retired B boys is that they have
credibility which would allow them to
gather people around them teams around
them and capital like they could it's
just sitting there unutilized if they're
doing nothing. um they have the
credibility in that people trust them as
a leader to be able to lead an
organization like that. They they could
have the same ideas and the same words
as somebody who's equally smart or
smarter and uh they'll still do better
for that. And so my point to them is you
have a responsibility not only as
someone who's who's got a lot of capital
yourself, but who's got this
underutilized resource of the ability to
do more uh uh if you're not doing that
then then are you really like what are
you even doing? Anyone can sit on a
boat. Few people can start another
multi-billion dollar company that does
something that matters. [applause] Yeah.
And the good news is most of them I
think uh I I I think a lot of people
have uh have gotten the itch to to solve
some of these problems that are out
there.
>> So we've got
>> nihilism is is is on is on the down.
>> The solution is we need more tea boys
and fewer B boys. [laughter]
>> Yeah, that's an interesting point.
Although
like I said, I think most of the tea
boys I think they seem like they keep
pretty busy. That's your point.
>> I don't I don't even I don't have a
problem with B boys who don't do enough.
Like some people they mis mistake what I
what I say like oh Palmer wants other
billionaires to work on defense or
energy or or biology and you like my
point is not that people need to
distract themselves by doing more
things. A lot of people can only do one
thing uh you know and that was what I
did for a long time. Uh it's what I hate
is the people who are not doing anything
that's that that is that is like a
repulsive to me. So maybe message to the
audience, you get to join the B boys
Slack group or whatever this is,
Telegram if you're doing something new
and differentiating.
>> The group the group actually got shut
down and uh we've been we've been
talking about now we need to do a B boys
2.0. Um but I think I think people post
>> maybe some B girls as well.
>> I think people posted the wrong memes a
few too many times.
>> Boom. I I look there there was there was
a time where there were no there were no
be girls and then there was this
Business Insider article uh whining
about it and uh the reality is like it's
just like me and some guys like you know
it's not like there's this isn't like
the Illuminati conference [laughter] you
know it's like they're like oh there's a
group and you know but no women have
been invited it's not that no women have
been invited it's just like me and some
some of my boys but
>> [laughter]
>> um but actually there there was a there
was there was a there was a girl at it
by the So, uh, we need Yeah, we need to
we need to restart that. We need to
restart that group.
>> So, you're in Facebook commercials now.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I'm so VR is out.
Uh, how does it compare against your
vision of what you wanted to achieve? Is
it?
>> Yeah.
>> Look, it does a lot of the things that
uh it's not exactly what I would make
were I the guy who's waving the magic
wand and and and
>> you got lots of magic wands
>> spinning the CAD. But uh um look, the
new MetaVR glasses are a lot closer in a
lot of ways. Uh so I've long been a
believer that you need to decouple the
compute and the battery from the head.
You should it should not be that and and
and I'm not even saying the head
totally. It's more the front. So before
Oculus Quest, so Oculus Quest was the
last thing that I worked on before they
fired me. And uh the prototypes at the
time were a prototype series code named
Santa Cruz. And uh we were actually
showing that publicly before they fired
me. And uh Santa Cruz had the battery
and compute on the back of the head and
then the light, you know, the part on
the soft tissue on the front of your
head was kept as light as possible. And
then at some point after they got rid of
me, they they jammed it all into one big
giant lump in the front and they ruined
the ergonomics. They forgot why you need
a top strap. Uh but you know, it it
bothers them, right? It bothers me most.
Look, it bothers me mostly at this point
because uh the Oculus Rift CV1, which
was the first modern consumer VR
headset. It got the ergonomics more or
less perfect
>> in 2016. And you know, we were showing
it off in 2015 and literally nobody has
done as good of as it and it's been over
a decade. Every single person screws it
up, even Apple. And I I just I don't I
can't comprehend it. How how could it be
that the ergonomic design led by a
19-year-old kid with no experience is
better than anything that anyone has
come up with since. Anyway, the new
Metavir glasses are the closest thing
and they're very lightweight. They've
offboarded the compute. They've
offboarded the batteries. They have
really high quality pass through. Um
they it has a feature that I invented
for CV1 called transformo fabric which
they do not call it. The basically using
uh fabric a a soft flexible fab black
black black lightabsorbing matte fabric
to one minimize reflections but two uh
basically seal the cavity between and
around the lenses. That means that you
can move them uh and the fabric just
stretches to meet where the lenses are
for different interpupilary distances
rather than having like sliding
mechanical interfaces and plastic. And
they brought Transformer fabric back for
the first time since my my era. So I'm
I'm I'm a huge fan and uh you know it's
a third of the price of Apple's product
and uh somewhat higher higher pixel
density. I I think that's pretty
extraordinary. Oh and and and 1/8 the
weight.
>> Amazing.
>> Amazing. Um,
>> let's close on let's close on this.
We've got, you know, 1500 entrepreneurs,
moonshot visionaries, and tens of
thousands watching on the live stream.
Uh, what's your advice?
What, you know, what did you learn in
high school that made you succeed at the
speed you did? We were talking about
this on the plane.
>> I mean, I I was really lucky to uh I
guess maybe not lucky, I did it. Uh, but
>> Well, you are you are lucky. That's
right. I am [laughter] lucky.
>> Similar name.
>> I started an online community called Mod
Retro when I was 14 or 15. Um, it was an
internet forum for people who were
modifying vintage game consoles and
computers, building handheld units,
improving the performance in a variety
of ways. We had a few thousand active
members and uh and a whole team of
volunteer moderators and administrators
with with me me at me at the top of it
for some reason. And uh I learned a lot
of valuable lessons about how you can
build an organization, how you market an
organization, how you get people to
believe in what you're doing. I learned
a lot about dealing with the types of
problems you deal with when you're
running a company, you know,
>> with humans.
>> Well, I mean, you you have two, it's a
tale as old as time. You've got two
people. They're both brilliant. They're
both very good at what they do, and they
hate each other, and they disagree over
something. you need to somehow mediate
the conflict or separate them in a way
that allows you to get the value that
that allows both of them to contribute
value to the greater project uh but not
have them hate you, not have them lose
faith in the broader thing, but also you
not not kill each other. Sometimes that
means you need to reconcile things
between the two. Sometimes it means that
you need to put one guy over here and
one guy over here and sometimes you need
to make sure that they don't know that
that's what you're doing as you do it.
That's [laughter] just I'm not saying
that's the key to running a successful
business is the management of the two problem. But it's you and once
you make it a threebody problem now
[laughter]
but uh but but it's it's that and a
hundred things like it that I learned
running Mod Retro that I was able to
take into starting Oculus to carry
forward into what I'm doing in my other
companies. And uh that that's why I'm
I'm a strong believer that that kids
should should should get a job. And I I
also had a job starting when I was 14.
So I learned how the real world worked,
too. But I I I'm a huge fan of people
doing things at a scale that's larger
than just themselves. In other words,
don't just do a project. Do a project
with someone else. Do a project with
other people. Build in the open. Learn
the the the the good parts of that, the
bad parts of that. It it it's been
extremely useful to me. And has building
changed in the age of AI? What advice do
you have? Again, you know, we've been
saying on the pod for a while now, you
know, forget about grad school. You
know, even college is a is a maybe you
didn't go to college. You know, in high
schoolers should what? Find a a purpose
they care about and use AI to go and
code it. What's your your closing advice
here on that?
You know, one of the reasons I have not
been as upset as some people about uh
No, that's funny. There's something on
the screen. It's telling us to not talk
about something. [laughter]
Just wanted to make sure you saw that.
>> I I I did. We're not going to talk about
my company.
>> All right. Great. Great. Um [laughter]
the uh there's there's a lot of people
who who love their craft and they love
what they do and uh and they are
rightfully mourning uh the end of for
example coding things by hand top to
bottom, start to finish as anything but
like a craft endeavor. Um, and and I and
I understand that it's it's the same way
that a lot of artists felt when the
camera was invented. They they whined
and complained about how it ruined art
and it made it so that anybody could
push a button and and you know, these
things are always painful for the people
who are masters of their craft. Um, I
already got screwed in that way a long
time ago. When you're a founder, you
don't get to actually work in any of the
tech anyway. All the other people get to
have all the fun. And so, you know, I I
like electrical engineering. I like
optical engineering. I like mechanical
engineering. I don't get to do any of it
because the job of a founder is to uh
hire people to to displace them and and
and to do what they thought they could
do or what they like they do like doing
better. Uh the job I've said many times
to people if you want to work on
technology uh work for somebody else. If
you want to work on non-stop
start a company. And and and so and so
what I would say to people is AI doesn't
actually change the part of the
job very much. you're still on the hook
legally. You're still on the hook for
all the interpersonal stuff. And you can
you you can delegate some of it, but at
the end of the day, it's your call. It's
your decision. It's the same thing for
fundraising. It's the same thing for
general product architecture. And when
people make the wrong decisions, it's
your choice as to when you need to
overrule them, override them, replace
them. I don't see AI replacing that part
of it anytime soon. Not because it
couldn't, but because the gains
everywhere else are so much larger that
I think we've got a good 10 years of
speed running all of the other parts of
the business before they before they
cover that. So, look, AI changes a lot.
But I I'm telling you, there's a lot of
people you are in for a rude awakening.
If you are like a hobbyist coder or a
hobbyist engineer and you think you're
going to start a company and you think
you're going to be doing all that stuff,
no, you're going to learn a hard lesson.
B being a founder was was always like AI
took your job. It's just that other
people took it.
>> Yeah.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, give it up for
Lucky.
[music]